A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Projects, Series L FA348
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Projects, Series L
1932-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Morrow, Hugh
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
FA348
104.5 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 L
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged alphabetically by topic, organization, or personal name.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Scope and Contents note
This general correspondence file offers extensive documentation on Nelson Rockefeller's business, civic, governmental, philanthropic, cultural, and social activities. Major files cover Dartmouth College's Committee on Economic Development, the Council for Inter-American Cooperation, the Council on Foreign Relations, the Institute for International Social Research, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), the Museum of Primitive Art (MoPA) founded by Rockefeller, the Whitney Museum of American Art,the Pan-American Union (Organization of the American States), Rockefeller Center, the United Jewish Appeal, the United Nations, the U.S. government, the Victory Clothing Drive for Overseas Relief, and the Westchester County Board of Health.
Many of the subject files in this series were periodically weeded of routine correspondence by the clerical staff at the Rockefeller family office. These files are identified with the line: "Some material previous to [date] discarded."
Philanthropy; Venezuela; United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; Public health -- Latin America; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; State governments -- United States; Social problems -- Latin America; National security -- United States; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); Economics; Education; New York (State); Philanthropy -- United States; Business; Business enterprises, Foreign; Arts; Brazil; Developing countries; Economic policy; Civic improvement; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Civics; Federal government -- United States; Government agencies; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Art, Primitive; Agriculture -- Latin America; Agriculture; Education -- Latin America; International relations; International relations -- United States; Latin America; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; International economic relations; Rockefeller family; United States. Office of Inter-American Affairs; Rockefeller, Mary (Mary Todhunter Clark); Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); Ruebhausen, Oscar M.; United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services; Museum of Primitive Art (New York, N.Y.); Morrow, Hugh; Hinman, George; American International Association for Economic and Social Development; Inter-American Development Commission; Whitman, Ann; International Basic Economy Corporation; United States. Dept. of State; United States. Dept. of State. Bureau of Western Hemisphere Affairs; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); United States. International Development Advisory Board; United States. President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization; United Nations
- A-Aj, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Appeals declined; requests for information; offers of objects for sale, declined; letters of criticism and political support. Some material previous to 1960 discarded.
- Ak-And, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ang-Am, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- As-Az, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Abbink, John - U.S. Technical Commission, Brazil, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Headed study of Brazilian economic fiscal situation. NAR suggestions as to what should be done in Brazil. Interest in study because of International Basic Economy Corporation. Correspondents include NAR, Berent Friele.
- Abbott, John E., 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Resignation as secretary of Museum of Modern Art for health reasons. Increasing illness. NAR assistance. Personal problems. Death.
- Academy of Political Science, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  NAR made life member 12/22/45. Notices of meetings, NAR speech 11/7/46.
- Acadia National Park, 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Letters and memos regarding management at Acadia, visits to the park, clippings, reactions to expansion of boundaries plan.
- Acknowledgments (A-H), 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Letters of thanks for clippings, books, food, letters, pictures, records; letter to NAR thanking him for kindness and flowers. Some material previous to 1955 discarded.
- Acknowledgments (I-P), 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Acknowledgments (Q-Z), 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Acknowledgments - Books (A-B), 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  NAR letters of appreciation for books sent. Many concern art, international affairs, political, social and economic problems. Placed in alphabetical order by authors' names, and previous to 1955 discarded.
- Acknowledgments - Books (C-D), 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Acknowledgments - Books (E-G), 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Acknowledgments - Books (H-L), 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Acknowledgments - Books (M-R), 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Acknowledgments - Books (S-Z), 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Adams, Orson, Jr., 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Arranged NAR speech before Pan American Society of Massachusetts, 1945, on Argentina and American system. (This was the speech which led to NAR's resignation from the Department of State.) Copy of speech not in file.
- Adler, Julius O., 1949 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Sends copy of a speech he made entitled "Milestones of Democracy."
- Advertising - Miscellaneous, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Correspondence re use of NAR's name in advertising, and advertising in Latin America.
- Advertising Council, Inc., 1949-1958 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Request for aid; invitations declined.
- African-American Organizations, 1957-1971 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Appeals, all declined.
- African-American Institute, The, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  NAR contribution for "The Sound of Africa," a show to benefit scholarship fund.
- Aged - Aging - Problems of, 1955-1971 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Appeals for aid for senior citizens' homes and organizations. All declined.
- Aguirre Baca, Dr. Francisco, 1948-1961 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Nicaraguan. Became political exile. Asked NAR for a job. His activities. Friendship for NAR.
- Agostini, Mrs. (Pauline Frances Stephens), 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Poet, widow of artist. Asked NAR for help. Comments on his election as Governor.
- Aid to Chinese Intellectuals, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Rockefeller Brothers Fund contribution toward refugee aid. NAR plans for contribution reversed.
- Air Transportation Association, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Request to join the Board of Directors of Air Transportation Association of America. Declined.
- Alaska, 1947-1967 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Efforts to interest NAR in Alaskan projects; all declined.
- Albany, New York, Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Appeals for local projects; all declined.
- Albany Civic Music Association, 1965-1969 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  NAR as annual member.
- Albany Institute of History and Art, 1959-1970 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Monroe Wheeler study of museum. Exhibition of NAR art at museum. NAR honorary chairman of advisory board. Special Contributions; Advisory Board meeting 4/28/59.
- Albany Institute of History and Art - Contributions, 1959-1971 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  $5,000 in 1959, $500 annually.
- Albany Joint Appeal Fund, 1958-1971 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  Formerly Albany Community Chest. NAR contributions.
- Albany Symphony Orchestra, 1959-1971 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  NAR annual contributions.
- Alcoholism - General Correspondence, 1947-1969 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  Appeals for support from Alcoholics Anonymous and other "dry" organizations; all declined.
- Alcoholism - National Council on Alcoholism, 1950-1970 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  NAR makes one time contribution in 1969.
- Alcorn, Hugh Meade (Honorable), 1957-1970 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  NAR best wishes when Alcorn made Republican National Chairman. NAR asks for help. Use of family plane.
- Aldrich, Alexander, 1957-1972 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  Support for NAR campaigns. NAR support for his campaigns. Changing positions in state government. Hudson River Valley Commission. Long Island University.
- Aldrich Family, 1952-1970 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  Requests for genealogy of Aldrich family. Some intra-famiy correspondence. Death of Martha Aldrich.
- Aldrich, Richard S. Jr., 1944-1969 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Aldrich, William T., Mr. and Mrs., 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  Invitation declined. Art exhibit by Mr. Aldrich.
- Alice in Wonderland, 1946-1953 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  NAR contribution towards Luther Evans' purchase of manuscript for presentation to the British Museum.
- Allen, Douglas Hedden, 1945-1953 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  President of the Rubber Development Corporation. His ideas for hemispheric peace. Comments on Communism in Latin America.
- Allen, William H., 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  Institute for Public Service. Allen's criticism of NAR policies and family history.
- Alliance for Progress, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  David Rockefeller's committee's comments and critique of Alliance for Progress.
- Alsop, Joseph and Stewart, 1955-1967 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  Friendship. Interviews.
- Alton, William A. & Mrs. Carol, 1938-1971 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  Personal friend of Winthrop Rockefeller and NAR, worked for Standard Oil in Germany, Egypt. NAR's efforts to assist him in the company. Worked for Rockefeller Center family offices, International Basic Economy Corporation. NAR provides office space for his independent venture. Engaged in Christian Science work.
- Amateur Athletic Union of the United States, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  NAR declines invitation to serve on Olympic Finance Committee.
- America-Israel Cultural Foundation, 1946-1971 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  NAR contributions to American Fund for Palestinian Institutions. Appeals made for America-Israel Cultural Foundation. NAR as contributor.
- American - Miscellaneous, 1958-1969 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  Appeals for contributions to various organizations. Most declined. NAR contributions for Parkinson's Disease. Several Israel and Arab organizations. American Civil Liberties Union.
- American Academy of Political and Social Sciences, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  NAR a life member.
- American Airlines, 1946-1960 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  Airline public relations material. NAR as "Admiral" of the airline.
- American Arbitration Association, 1938-1956 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  NAR declined participation in Association and its subsidiary, The Inter-American Arbitration Commission. Correspondents include NAR, John E. Lockwood.
- American Associations, 1940-1969 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  Appeals. Association of French Artists, Association of Advancement of Science, Association for a Democratic Germany.
- American Brazilian Association, 1947-1952 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  NAR contributes toward development of Cultural and Social Relations between United States and Brazil.
- American-Chinese Committee of the MEM - Rural Reconstruction, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  NAR gives $10,000 toward rural reconstruction in China.
- American Committee on United Europe, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  Organized American support for European unity. NAR did not particpate. Correspondents include NAR, Allen Dulles, W. J. Donovan.
- American Committee on United Europe - Contributions, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  1950 Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributes $10,000.
- American Council for Democratic Greece, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  On Justice Department list as Communist Front. NAR asked to become a sponsor. Declined.
- American Council for The International Promotion of Democracy Under God (C.I.P.), Inc., 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  NAR contributes $10,000 in 1963 to the "Pro Deo" University in Rome. Later appeal ignored.
- American Council for Judaism, 1949-1958 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  Anti-Zionist organization. Requests for statements from NAR declined.
- American Council for Nationalities Service, 1948-1963 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  Formerly Common Council for American Unity. Worked for understanding among minority groups. Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributions in 1948 and 1963.
- American Council of Learned Societies, 1945-1953 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  NAR declines request to comment on Inter-American intellectual interchange.
- American Council of Voluntary Agencies for Foreign Service, Inc., 1947-1958 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  NAR asked to head fund drive; declined. Other appeals declined. Correspondents include NAR, Arthur W. Packard.
- American Council on Education, 1947-1964 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  Efforts to interest NAR in Council. Declined. NAR contributions to Mexican-American Institute of Cultural Relations in 1954.
- American Federation of Arts, 1951-1971 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  NAR contributions to support of "Magazine of Art." Requests for loans of NAR's art declined. Mr. and Mrs. NAR members of Art Collectors Club of America.